[Music]
hello everyone welcome to Dynamics 3
city5 business Central launch event my
name is andaro I'm the principal program
manager for a Dynamics 365 buiness
Central and today I would like to show
uh what's new in resource governor for
Dynamics 365 buiness Central
online so the agenda for today's uh
session is first I will talk about the
resource governance Mission and then I
will tell you a little story about the
uh resource governance uh history for uh
Business Center Online where we came
from where we are today and where we are
going in the future in uh increasing the
elasticity availability and throughput
for your workloads in the cloud and then
I will show you a little bit of um um
illustration of what is a shared
multi-end architecture where your
workload will run in the cloud and I
will show you uh the biggest investment
that we did last year which is resource
consumption tracking that allows us to
improve a lot of areas in the elasticity
of our service and then uh one of the uh
the most recent Improv Improvement uh
that we will announce with this release
is a new operational limits that will be
previewed throughout this uh next
quarter and I will at the end we I will
show you um the preview practicalities
what can you expect throughout this um
preview period so without uh further Ado
let's um let's talk about the resource
governance
Mission so the mission for resource
governance in business Central onine is
to offer optimal and fair resource
consumption to all Dynamics 365 Business
Center Online customer optimal means we
want to offer maximal availability and
performance for all resource consumption
with minimal redundancy minimal uh eidle
resources right uh fair means we want to
treat all customer and their user
equally with respect to capacity and at
the same time proportionally with
respect to the licenses we want to
ensure that all our customer and their
user can consume how and what they can
consume in their entitled manners what
they are entitled to consume which is
the license specific features how much
we want to ensure that they can consume
as much as possible as long as it is
covered by their licenses this is where
we will introduce A New Concept that
does not exist in Business Center online
before which is called entitlement
quotas we are planning to introduce this
concept of quotas in the next uh uh few
seme
from now and how fast can can they
consume we want to ensure they can
consume resources uh when I'm talking
about resources it means like uh web
service request resources or compute
resources or storage resources we want
to allow or ensure customer can consume
as fast as possible we want to give top
speed to all user as long as their
consumption does not adversely impact
others and this is the concept that you
are already familiar with which is
called operational limits so um before I
go uh go on I would like to give a a
quick um uh introduction of what the
difference between quotas and limits
because sometimes people confuse them so
a qua in governance terminology quas are
like entitlements or rights where
customer and their user can claim or
exercise those right while limits are
laws or rules that you need to follow so
essentially when you want to exercise
your right or you want to claim your
entitlement you can do that as long as
your follow the laws and rules right at
the user level quotas are tiered that
means like different licenses has
different um uh level of quotas right
and they are cumulative that means uh in
a customer when you have um when you buy
more licenses the amount of quot
accumulated such that all users in that
um in that uh environment can actually
consume those cumulative quotas and also
transferable is if one user doesn't use
his his quot other user cannot uh use
more than uh what he uh that that's
entitled for his license right and um
for limits it's actually different for
limits they are fixed that means all
user have the same amount of limit that
they have to follow and they are equal
applicable to all user and
non-transferable that means if one user
uh for example follow the speed limit of
a web service request uh let's say we
have a 1,000 request per minute and they
can only they um they submit a request
for 500 does not mean the next user can
submit like 1,500 everybody has to for
the same limit which is 1,000 requests
per minute for example okay so now let
me tell you a little of history of where
we came from like um our story start
like really recently in 2018 where
there's a general availability of
Dynamics 365 business Central online in
that year we've we lifted and shifted
business Central into Azure to run on a
shared multitalent architecture a
software as a service or a SAS
architecture when we built this elastic
service we actually um follow the the
the traditional technique for elasticity
which is mounting uh environments on
multiple server instances or multiple
VMS or host right balancing workloads
across those many hosts that mounted and
grouping host uh or or servers to serf
different environments and also adding
new host which is scaling out so so
these four technique which is mounting
balancing grouping and scaling are what
I like fondly called the force Horseman
of elasticity right so when we are
building our elastic service at the same
time we actually already must govern uh
resource consumption in the cloud so we
started with very conservative
operational limits and we don't really
introduce um u a definite quota so right
now we don't have a in we still have an
indefinite quotas right and uh recently
last year we started to track resource
consumption so basically we want to
track all type of workload and capacity
unit for example number of tasks number
of requests number of session execution
time memory consumption storage
consumption all those uh um uh capacity
unit we want to track for every user for
every environment and for every customer
at any given moment and period this
allow us to lay the foundation to
improve our elasticity techniques so as
our service mature we are actually able
to start uh uh creating more intelligent
mounting intelligent balancing grouping
and scaling as well as offer more
expensive limits and quantifiable
quotas so let me show um just a quick um
illustration of what is a shared and
multier architecture
is we start with the compute layer uh
imagine like there's a compute cluster
that has a uh each cluster has many um
uh uh virtual machine or host right and
each uh all of those host can share uh
can be uh group into different um uh
host groups and on the storage layer we
have a database server where inside the
uh the server you can have multiple pool
which are uh resources shared by um a
separate tenant databases right so
imagine you have let's say you have four
environment T1 T2 T3 and T4 that
actually sharing the the same host um
host resources and they are connecting
to the separate tenant databases in the
in the in the in the database layer
right so if you notice uh when we
starting for example 10 and 2 10 and
three and 10 and four they are needing
more um um uh Computer Resources you can
actually Mount those um environment on
more host for example in the second host
you mounting ton 2 3 4 and five and then
they're connecting to the their own uh
Tenon data um tenant database in the in
the database server right and you can do
the same when you have um more um um uh
computer resources needed for those
Tenon and you can see in this picture
Tenon um uh environment three four and
five are actually mounted on three host
that means like they actually have the
resources of three hose now um if you
actually notice for example tenant
database four and five needing more
juices for example they are running um a
long running queries you can actually um
uh upgrade their pool such as they going
to a different pool that has more
resources for those databases so in this
picture uh T4 and T5 ton databases are
moving to pool two that should have a
less density and more resources for long
running queries for example and you can
do the same scaling independently uh
compute layer um from the database layer
in this case uh let's say um 10 and four
and five need more comput resources we
can see that we only have three host in
the computer cluster we can actually
scale out and add more more hoses and
more host like two more host and then
like can you can actually Mount and T4
and T5 and group them in this new um uh
new group of host so in that case T4 and
T5 will have more juice more compute
resources to run like for example
parallel task parallel web service
request Etc so that's a quick uh
introduction of a Shar multitan
architecture right so let's talk about
about the resource consumption tracking
when we do actually are able to track uh
all the resource consumption you can see
in this picture right um the cluster
that I mentioned before is like this big
uh rectangular um diagram and inside
each of this um inside of this cluster
you have all these resources you have
the NST which is the server instance to
run your workload you have Gateway that
handle your web service request etc etc
the first thing that we do is actually
create a new service which is called
local consumption tracker and this local
consumption tracker are really uh there
to implement operational limits so it it
actually track all consumption of
resources per user and per environment
in each cluster the next service that we
create for consum tring is the global
consumption tracker and this service is
really um uh instrumental to implem uh
entitlement quotas in the future the job
of global consumption tracker is to
basically aggregate all uh resource
consumption from local local um
consumption tracker the lcts in each
cluster and aggregate it across the
whole Tenon and then apply it to uh the
customer wide uh quotas
okay so what we what we gain with
consumption tracking is essentially in a
lot lighter side we kind of like uh
going from no or not not having any or
shortterm memory into having a long-term
memory So like um like the myth that
they're saying uh goldfish has no memory
and elephant has a long-term memory we
actually turning business Central online
from a goldfish into an elephant because
now we actually can remember all type of
consumption patterns for each tenon for
an illustration I can show you one of
this diagram for example in this diagram
we knows that like uh one Tenon uh in a
in a tracking period for 1 hour between
noon and 1 p.m. is actually only picking
at 1210 so you can see um uh it doesn't
actually uh consume resources all the
time they are only pi Peck period where
it it consume more than uh other times
right now if you have all this type of
consumption pattern for multiple tenants
you can actually group those tenant or
environment that doesn't pick at the
same time such that they don't overlap
when they have a burst consumption in
this case when you have more and more
Tenon you can actually um put them
together in a resources where the
resources are actually sufficient to uh
to support all this um tenants for
example in 20 tenants you don't really
need um uh 20 times pick uh pick um
consumption because if you make sure
that the their consumption pattern does
not overlap then you can actually um
manage an optimal resource governance
for um uh for these tenants okay so now
uh let me talk about the key Improvement
areas that enabled by this um uh by the
new resource consumtion tracking the
first thing that we are able to do is
offering an operational limit that are
fair and expensive first we will public
Lish a clear user based limit if you
probably notice uh most of our
operational limits are envir
environmental based and environment
based right now is we're going to
publish a clear user based limit that
protect our service ensure fairness
among users and Inspire elasticity and
scalability the ETA for this um uh new
user base limit will be throughout this
uh next quarter which is Art fourth
quarter of calendar uh 2023 right and at
the same time under the hood we also
applying a dynamic resource-based limit
this is not published but this is
something that we use underneath our
service to make sure that um our service
are are always uh scalable um um is
protected and uh ensure fairness among
customer and environment so the user
based limits uh are there to ensure
fairness among users while the resource
based limits are there to ensure
fairness among customers or environment
and this is ongoing and continuous uh
Improvement throughout the year
okay the second thing that we are able
to improve with the resource consumption
tring like I mentioned before you are we
are able to improve the elasticity
techniques so we can actually do
intelligent balancing mounting grouping
and
scaling because the consumption pattern
and the limit exhaustion signals can be
used to actually distribute or rebalance
workload more intelligently across
mounted to and mount more environment on
M hose a group hose differently for
example like um heavy um heavy uh
consuming uh uh Tenon will go with a
less heavy consuming tening such that
they can actually uh balance each other
out for example and you can also like um
use the signal of limit exhaustion and
consumption pattern to scale out and add
more host into the cluster so we the aim
is like we want to make sure that we uh
exploit all this technique before you
actually throttle throttle which should
be as a last resort if we cannot
actually expand our service to aob your
workload right and this is continuous
ongoing Improvement throughout the year
and finally we want to uh introduce
entitlement quotas and flexible access
consumption and we will publish a user
based and tenant white quotas for licens
and unlicensed user respectiv
respectively and allow buying access
consumption this should be um estimated
happening in the next two or three
semester from now uh the aim is like uh
99% of our customer will be able to um
um uh to consume resources under their
quota not not a lot of them will exceed
it but for some of the customer who
wants to exceed their consumption will
allow them option to buy more add-on
capacity or pay for pay as you go for
their excess
consumption so all these Improvement
will be applied in at many different
type of resources we'll focus more on
the web service request handling
resources first Computer Resources next
and then later on on the uh database or
storage
resources so let's talk about like um
the new operational limits that's coming
this quarter okay before I talk about um
uh what's the new operational limits
that's coming let me introduce you the
concept of um operational limit because
there are three type of operational
limits that we can actually use to uh
govern resources in the cloud there are
essentially for a complete governance
you need to speed limit concurrency
limit and execution time limit for this
I'd like to use a loose analogy of a
like a highway um Highway management
traffic management okay if you imagine a
stretch of a highway as um a limited
server or host capacity traversing that
Highway represent consuming a portion of
that capacity and cars in that Highway
represent workload submitted by our
customer and their users in this case um
the customer or user are colorcoded like
a blue customer green orange and yellow
right so in this case uh in this analogy
all users should enter or merge their
traffic into the highway at the certain
speed limit they should not exceed that
speed limit right and then higher toll
charges that you pay for represent how
far you can go so that's actually
representing the premium licenses that
you can buy to consume more um uh
quotas so first uh let me introduce what
is a speed limit means in speed limits
uh speed limit essentially uh in the
highway analogies to control how fast
cars enter to the highway so in Business
Center online or um in somewhere service
it is to control how fast workloads
enter our system so if all um cars are
entering the the highway more or less
under the super limit you can actually
imagine the highway capacity will fill
up with more or less the same number of
blue cars green cars yellow or orange
right when the capacity is fill up you
might want to redirect traffic to other
uh accessible haway that is representing
rebalancing workload in our uh BC online
right and then or you might actually
want to like um opening up more Highway
that accessible for certain customer
that that's represent mounting more
environment to more host in a cluster or
even for example um uh dedicating some
Highway for just blue or orange car that
essentially grouping those um um uh
grouping those um uh uh workloads that
uh need more resources for example and
finally you can basically build a new
highway from scratch which represents
scaling out in our in our uh BC online
World
okay so the next concept is a
concurrency limit uh by the way speed
limit and concurrence limits already
exists in our business Central online it
just right now it's still in on a per
environment basis so we will introduce a
per user basis later on so in a
concurrency limits essentially imagine
all cars are entering the highway more
or less under the spit limit but there
are the there are blue cars that coming
from different entry point so you end up
with like more blue cars at the same
time in the in the highway and that
cannot be controlled with spit limits so
we have to introduce new limit which is
concurrency limit to control how many
car are present at any given moment in
the highway or in our road
in BC online to control how many
workloads are concurrently processed in
the
system now um we actually already have
this spit limit and congruence limit
what we are missing that the in the
future that we would like to introduce
is a new limit which is called execution
time limit so imagine in this highway
analogy when you have cars coming coming
in at the under the the spit limit and
they are actually not entering uh the
highway from multiple entry point but
some of this car are actually stretch
limousine or a long trailer or truck and
you can imagine in the capacity of the
highway fill up with this long stretch
blue car so that's a represent
essentially a long running workload in
our system so we need a new limit uh an
additional to speed and concurrency
limit which is execution time limit to
control how long workload up process in
our
system so the preview that's coming this
next quarter is first um in the early um
uh early quarter uh next quarter we will
actually uh upgrade the old concurrency
limit for scheduled tasks from three
concurrently running tasks per
environment into five concurrently
running tasks per user so I can imagine
now if you have more user in the
environment the true put for for your
environment can get bigger you have for
example you have two user you can run
like a 10 scheduled task in parallel or
if you have treer you can run 15 tasks
in parallel previously you can only run
three per environment so this is a a
huge uh increase in the throughput for
your workload okay the next Improvement
that we planning is actually changing
the speed limit from the old for web
service request from the old 600 um uh
requests per environment per minute into
actually 6,000 requests per user in the
previous 5 minute sliding window so this
actually gives you flexibility to have a
burst pick of um uh requests for example
if you want to have in the first minute
to have 6,000 you can do that you as
long as you make sure that across a 5
minute sing window you maintain the
number of um uh requests in that in that
period okay so that is coming in the mid
quarter um which is around around
November uh November December time
timeline right and finally another
concurrency limit that we will introduce
is the web also for web service request
and this time we not changing the number
too much what we changing is the
denominator of this limit so before we
are um we are allowing only 10
concurrently handled um uh web service
request where five is processed and 95
cued uh per environment now we actually
allowing per user so we we are opening
up the uh parallel U parallel web survey
request 10 100 the same number 100
concurrently handle five uh process and
95 cute but per user so that means like
when you have environment with more user
you get more trut that's the uh that's
the last Improvement for this quarter
that be aiming at the end of this
quarter okay and finally in the future
you can expect the introduction of the
execution time limit that I mentioned
before for example uh if you if we have
like um a server instant with like four
cores right in a 5 minute elapse time of
sliding window that four core actually
allow 4 * 5 20 minute execution time so
within that 20 minute execution time
what is the X minute that we allow per
user to consume and then underneath that
under the hood we will actually make
sure that each environment does not
consume up to y% of the total execution
time or z% of the total execution time
in a cluster so those are uh limits that
coming in the future that we plan uh for
uh incoming releases so uh finally uh I
would like to show the preview practic
alties what can you expect throughout
this uh preview period so throughout um
October November December we are
actually making sure that this
operational limit are continue to be
monitored and fine-tuned pro to provide
higher trp than the old one so uh expect
expect it to change a lot sub it's
subject to change right and the
throughput will not be uh in a will not
be increased in a big bang manner right
like uh you you will not see like for
example currently you are only run three
concurrent tasks per uh per environment
um um per environment and suddenly you
will see like a unlimited number of Tas
in parallel per en per per environment
right that's not going to happen but
we're going to do it gradually so we
will do a gradual uh throughput increase
let me just give you an illustration for
example we will increase it from U from
three to six or or nine um nine parallel
task for um per environment and then we
monitor um the the situation and then we
keep increasing it three times four
times five times we keep continue
increasing until we have an optimal
optimal throughput that we can provide
right and that is essentially what we
plan so we want to make sure that um we
uh communicate those incremental uh
increase of throughput throughout the
the quarter throughout the uh the
preview period uh we'll announce any
changes in our release plan so watch out
for the minor uh 23x releases and also
Alo in other documentation especially
the operational limit documents because
there's going to be a lot of um updates
in the document uh throughout the period
okay and finally we always appreciate
your feedback and suggestion uh please
use our Yammer channel to to contact us
to tell us what have you been um
monitoring and what you see in uh in
term of your your um uh throughput for
your workloads right and uh give us
feedback and suggestion so continue um
uh getting getting back to us using uh
the yam
our documentation our Twitter and uh
also uh please join us sign up for BC
office hour especially if it's relevant
with the resource governance uh upgrades
in the
future so thank you and uh with that uh
that conclude our session I look forward
to seeing you soon um in the Q&A
sessions uh remotely and also in person
in directions conference thank thank you
for your attention see you
soon